Did you know that it is estimated that a 4 and a
8% of the world's population has a
attention deficit disorder with or
without hyperactivity you know that most
of people do not know and go to
consultation with symptoms of depression and
anxiety come to treat their symptoms
but behind that there is a
attention deficit today here we are going to
talk about the topic so you can
identify the causes What symptoms give us
will produce this disorder and the
solutions we have are
Marisa Marzá clinical health psychologist
and I welcome you to Understanding Your Mind
mind after years as a professional
psychology and attending to different
patients or clients, I have been able to
find that some of them that
present symptoms of anxiety or
depression does not improve or there are difficulties
At the time they join the
treatment they abandon they do not do the
tasks and their evolution since it does not improve today
the surprise of discovering that behind
of these cases of depression and
Anxiety is like the symptoms, not the
origin the origin could be after the
proper diagnosis of a disorder
attention deficit with or without
hyperactivity this What does it mean that
many people who come for consultation
who come to solve their problems
anxiety or depression and we are
applying tools and strategies
for that we are as wrong as ever
time to apply the appropriate treatment
Why Because the real origin is
another and the symptoms are going to be the
anxiety and depression which is the cause of
the ones they are coming but we have to make one
good exploration to identify that
there may be a deficit disorder
attention in the new studies already
you can check that there is a problem
neurobiological is a disorder of the
biological development where you are
people a part of the brain that is
responsible for fixing attention is not
active with the same let's say
synchronicity that what would be a
brain
typical we are facing a New Vision of
the
psychology also from neuroscience
where these two currents converge
We can help people better one by one
to really identify what the
problem and two give him the tools
to be able to solve it and improve it
quality of life we are going to explain a
little bit What is this about
disorder is a disorder as we have
said of the
neurodevelopment, that is, throughout
life is going to present itself the brain is
develops at a pace and speed
more or less determined and these people
They will have a more neurodevelopmental
slow the studies tell us that there is
areas of the brain that will not present
the thickness determined for example by the
cerebral cortex and other areas that do not
I'm going to go into depth, we'll do another one
presentation where we explain this
better but you can already see it thanks to the
technology that really both the
Children and adults present a
lack of synchronicity in activation
of certain areas of the brain that
They are the ones that allow us to focus our attention
in a prolonged and long-term manner
And this is going to generate a type of symptoms
that will bring problems to the
people and that is what will later bring
those depressions or those anxieties this
It would be the biological part, there has been
There are many professionals who have a lot of dilemma
They think that there are no professionals
who think so but if we base ourselves
in the scientific method and in the
studies is as visualized that
There really is a disharmony in the
functioning of a specific area of the
brain as regards the area
psychological What happens to the person who
This neurodivergence has what
It is assumed that it has been damaged, there are theories
What executive functions tell us
They have an execution problem, it is a
area of the brain that is responsible for
regulate the actions that occur between me
I have an intention to do something and
take action this impasse of
intention and action we have a brief
space of time where the acts
executive functions is a part of the
brain that helps me direct the
behavior to move to action or to inhibit
certain behaviors like I don't want
do nothing or I get distracted by anything
a matter of both inhibition and action
that lead me to take appropriate action
To achieve my goal this is what I
people have damaged this area and
Therefore this intention can be
have Clara can have Clara too
What is the action they have to do?
but the synchronization between intention and
action does not occur It does not cost much or
It supposes a great deal of
effort other theories also give us
They say there is a deficiency in La
regulation of dopamine adop and by
simplify we have an area that is
called nucleus accumbens in the brain
where dopamine is what does the
effect and this dopamine is the hormone that
It allows me to do long-term projects
term
Em let's say it will allow me to have the
sufficient motivation over time
enough for me to be able to poster
a reward over time if
For example, I have the goal of going to
gym and I know that the effects are going to happen
see in 6 months let's say dopamine is the
that will regulate motivation will
continue to have its effect on me so that
I stayed for 6 months going to
gym and then have the reward
Well, these people are in my physical health.
people are going to have the problem that
This has to be done in the long run
this dopamine will not take effect in the long term
and long before reaching the goal
They will become demotivated and will stop doing things.
those tasks that they have to do for
reach their goal or they will become demotivated and
They will abandon the task taking into account
count these two, let's say, aspects of
executive functions and a dopamine that
it's not having the effect it should
doing is what is going to cause all the
symptoms of attention deficit
what is that symptomatology on the one hand
we are going to have symptoms of inattention
And others are going to be symptoms of
hyperactivity here I want to clarify that
It is called hyperactivity but in
truth is not hyperactivity it is a
hyper impulsivity to be
hyperactive we can have a lot
there is a need for movement and action
people who are very energetic and
we can confuse with that hyperactivity
but it would be more of a hyper impulsiveness
say they are not able to
self-regulate these behaviors more than
generate eh activity the hyperactive knows
what he is doing because he is doing it
doing no no for maybe at all
day but it has its objectives, its goals
clear And regulates its behavior accordingly
of its energy which may be very high but
There is no such thing as hyper impulsivity
intention between this intention and this
action and there is no such synchronicity and
What there is is a lot of impulsiveness, no
Any stimulus will generate a
answer that I do not govern it is
govern my own impulsiveness
So leaving this clear,
symptomatology of the
Inattention will be because you cannot put
the focus on something I have to do
enough
I'm going to be distracted for a long time. Eh, I'm not going to
be able to capture the necessary information
maybe to learn something new I'm going to
have difficulty following
instructions
and I'm going to start avoiding all the
activities or tasks that mean a
extra effort because impulsiveness
will make you flee or escape from those
situations do not cause me discomfort
keep the focus of attention these
would be symptoms that then evidently
in our daily life will bring
many problems to solve
conflicts of
learning of
sociability with my relationships
interpersonal that we will go
breaking down after and on the other side
we are going to have this hyper impulsiveness
where the person is going to show how a
restlessness where perhaps he has tics moves
the hands, the feet, not the leg
bites what could be pens
pencils have a constant need
to move, he cannot sit for long
while he gets up he sits down it costs him
very much also how to maintain the
attention on something You can go back
even appearing rude is also going to
there may be verbal impulsiveness
talking too much being interrupting
when another speaks And that will also
bring many problems at the time of
social interaction and they will also
to be very impatient is not the case
wait for the reward for what we have
dopamine saying wait for something
happens they will not hold out and they will
abandon no Or they are going to leave if there is one
very long line, well they're going to leave no no
They will wait their turn and go to
anticipating will generate all this for them
much anguish we must understand that this
Everything has a biological root why
because many times these people are
He calls them lazy and rude
eem that they have no willpower that
They are not motivated by anything, as if they don't care
everything and it is not like that no It is simply that
this
divergence makes this much more difficult for them
more difficult than for the rest of the
people Robert sapolsky describes very
well as this part of the brain that is
the one in charge of doing things
difficult when you have to do them
say this part of the charge that is going to us
to activate in order to be able to do what
We do not want to make the majority of
people if these work well for us
people are not activated therefore in
the moment when something needs to be done with
difficulty do not have this part that they
help therefore life will be for them
They have to put it much more complicated
much more effort than other people and
the results are going to be much more
poor people, we don't have this with us
confuse with a disability
intellectual or who have a low feib or
that they do not have the intelligence
skills or tools yes
They have but they can't or don't know how
apply it in the appropriate manner in the
right time we'll see that thanks
to cognitive behavioral therapy
we can develop these
skills in a different way to
that they can be achieved, not the
long-term tasks that want
achieve or the goals they want
getting these people there is something that
I also
I would like it because they talk to me about it
diagnosis no How is that done
diagnosis the diagnosis Yes there is
neurobiological tests that can be
do I think not everyone can
access them but a good professional
specialized a psychiatrist a psychologist
a urologist with a clinical interview
well done, attentive and exploring well, eh
Your history will be able to diagnose
appropriate manner to these people
diagnosis is not qualitative. That is to say
you either have it or you don't, there is a big
broad
spectrum of
possibilities and differences with the
same disorder even people who do not
have this diagnosis may present
this type of symptoms in a way
punctual therefore the diagnosis will
be more
quantitative What will be the
differentiator when the amount of
symptoms that appear in the person
have the weight that is making it difficult for me
my life is going to have psychological damage
there is emotional damage, they are going to see one
series of symptoms in your life will be seen
affected your life in a way
significant because of this
inability to focus attention
to persist in tasks in order to be able
respond appropriately to what
what one wants then is not
qualitative is not whether you have it or you don't have it
but a very good evaluation must be made
exhaustive To what extent that is
making life difficult or not
person therefore always has to be
a specialized professional who can
diagnose it now what
treatments we have since we have since
the part that would be the medical part
um, I'm not going to go into details here.
but they are going to be
eh medications that what they are going to
to do is to activate the dopamine that is in
brain for this deficiency that we were talking about
and it will help that brain to be able to
function in a more
synchronized with what is intended
But here too there is a lot of dilemma there
cases that work and cases that don't
It works and if it is good to medicate no
I'm not going to medicate there, but let it be known
that there is that medication that in in
some cases may be helping aa
keep the focus on these people by
On the other hand, we have that this is my
part of cognitive behavioral therapy
in which we are going to help these
people to be able to direct find
strategies and above all to change
thoughts or distortions that may
having many here will ask and why
that cognitive-behavioral therapy
It can help if we are talking about that
It is a biological disorder, there is no one
a biological divergence How
therapy can help because therapy
Cognitive behavioral therapy can help from
two very important positions one is the
to find eh tools
behavioral to move to this action of
the one we were talking about that costs them a lot and
how In what way this action
we can perpetuate in time that we do not
abandon Then there are strategies
specific to be able to calculate it
time because it is another of the
difficulties they have do not have the
perception of the passage of time
time they don't know how to calculate it and it is a
way to teach them to manage time
in a visual way of how to organize
planning your tasks have many
problems in the organization of what
It would be the achievement of long-term goals
deadline they do not know that planning and it is
teaches in steps so that it can be successful
much more digestible and easier for them
as in small tasks that are
capable of carrying out such tasks
small tasks can then
transform into a gr gr objective a
great task that would serve on one hand but
for another that seems to me
more interesting is the part of the
Cognition is the part of
thinking as it is a disorder that
It comes from childhood and is already presented
have a history of
failures or have a history of
trying to achieve things that never happen or
scolding or verbalizations by
educators or parents who in the
ignorance, they label us as lazy
rude, incapable or even little educated
intelligent and it has nothing to do with it
then this cognition these
thoughts they have about them
themselves on their ability will influence
totally also when taking
actions of people with disorders
attention deficit disorder
hyperactivity will escape many
sometimes situations will be avoided
situations that already have a history
of failures, why am I going to do it again?
try Yes total
I'm never going to get it and it doesn't have that much
to do with self-esteem because they
many times they know that they are capable of
They have the skills, they have the
tools but in what not
They trust in their ability to regulate themselves
What is different is not that they know what
you have to do it, you know you can do it
because they have the skills but
What they distrust is that they are not going to be
capable of
maintain continuity over time
time to do that For example in the case
of going to the gym they know that for
to have their physical health they have to go to the
gym they know there is no need
convince them know how to do it I pay my
fee and I go for an hour a day and I go to
get it know how You have to do it
but they don't trust that everyone will go
the days not this ligament that is between
intention and action is what
failure in his past experience takes it
with great desire But they know they can
go two or three days and leave abandoned
the task then cognitive therapy
behavioral will consist of one in which
understand with psychoeducation what it is
really the problem The problem is
biological two that has nothing to do with
with his worth his abilities but yes with
its capacity to
self-regulation that will be provided to them
of the necessary tools so that
those thoughts and those avoidances that
They are going to do a task that will
suppose an effort can confront it
from another place and from believing that yes
they will be able to
regulate it from there upon success
perhaps in the first goals that they can
getting is going to start to
change everything that is your system
beliefs about their abilities and
we are going to enter into a dynamic of acting
to regulate and do the things that suit them
will start helping and getting their
goals for the people who are around me
listening and suspect or already know that they have
this is this
disorder have to do with the
therapy what they are going to get is a
new way of approaching life is going to be
a rediscovery and a
reconstruction of how to communicate or
give focus to life not how things are going
to fully apply tools
different why
because they come from a totally different background
constantly inconstant They do not
They know what stability is, they don't know
what is constancy and there is no one
base place to return to if we don't have to
go to a new place to build each
A person is a world. Each person is going to be
build let's say your specific material
so that he can get by in life
and achieve those goals they want
the role of therapy
It is that the person takes action
The ultimate goal is for it to work and be able to
get all those achievements
purposes that you want so that your
life is fuller or has more
well-being has a component
genetic very important figures
They talk about a
7% that surely some relative of yours
will have either the grandparents or the parents or
the children brothers So if we have
the suspicion that someone has there is that
explore the entire family circle because
surely more people have and it would be
So it is appropriate to be able to give them this
information so that they can obtain and
the necessary tools because the
symptoms or consequences of not
taking care of ourselves are what lead us to
severe anxiety disorders
severe depression if not treated and
also at a high rate of
dopamine addictions
Then it would be advisable to
could identify as soon as possible if
you have children that you may suspect that
may have simply to give them those
tools or the right approach for your
children to your partner
aa your brothers and that there is no
environment where the fool is the one who does not
He knows that a lazy person is all this type
of terminology that can harm
significantly because the life of the
person I would like to point out that it is not
a disease and as it is not one
disease is not cured is a
neurodivergence don't feel bad
if you suspect you have it or if you already have it
have been diagnosed with simple
you have to get the tools that
they suit you and your neurodivergence
Well, in order to get yours
achievements your goals the well-being that
you want in your life I hope this
information has been to your liking and we
see you next time
episode if you liked the content
Subscribe to the Channel and don't forget to
leave
[Music]